Preliminary Guide to the History of Economics Society Records, 1971-2016 RL.00550
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
History of Economics Society records
1971-2016
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
History of Economics Society
RL.00550
37.5 Linear Feet
The History of Economics Society was established in 1974 and currently has over 300 members. Through meetings, conferences, and its publication, Journal of the History of Economic Thought, HES seeks to promote communication, dessiminate knowledge, and encourage inquiry into the history of economics. Collection contains membership and financial records, papers and proceedings of annual meetings, officer's correspondence, constitution and bylaws, copies of the History of Economics Society Bulletin, and correspondence and papers related to the Society's Elgar publications. Also included are accepted and rejected manuscripts from the Society's journal, the Journal of the History of Economic Thought.
Access Restrictions
Collection is restricted.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The History of Economics Society records were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a gift in 1990-2009, 2015, 2016, and 2017.
Historical Note
The History of Economics Society was established at the University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill in 1974, and today has over 300 members from around the world. It sponsors an annual conference as well as other meetings throughout the year, and since 1990 has published the Journal of the History of Economic Thought. According to its website, the Society has three main goals: to promote interest and inquiry into the history of economics and other related areas of intellectual history; to provide avenues of communication between scholars and researchers in the field of the history of economics; and to dessiminate knowledge about the history of economics.
Collection Overview
Collection contains membership and financial records, papers and proceedings of annual meetings, officer's correspondence, constitution and bylaws, copies of the History of Economics Society Bulletin, and correspondence and papers related to the Society's Elgar publications. Also included are accepted and rejected manuscripts from the Society's journal, the Journal of the History of Economic Thought.
Economic history -- Societies, etc.; Economics -- Societies, etc.; Goodwin, Craufurd D. W.; Hirsch, Abraham; Moss, Laurence S., 1944-; Samuels, Warren J., 1933-; Whitaker, John K. (John King); Coats, A. W. (Alfred William), 1924-; Rutherford, Malcolm, 1948-; Rutherford, Malcolm, 1948-
- History of Economics Society Records, 1971-1991, 12 boxes
  Scope and Contents note
  Collection (9054 items; dated 1971-1991) contains membership and financial records, papers and proceedings of annual meetings, officer's correspondence, constitution and bylaws, copies of the History of Economics Society Bulletin, and correspondence and papers related to the Society's Elgar publications. Many of the files were generated by Laurence S. Moss, as the Society's Secretary-Treasurer. Other officers from whom materials were received include William J. Barber, Abraham Hirsch, John K. Whitaker, Warren Samuels, Craufurd Goodwin, A.W. Coats, and Vincent J. Tarascio.
  - Acc. 1990-0002 (Box 1-9)
  - Acc. 1990-0075 and Acc. 1991-0146 (Box 1)
  - Acc. 1993-0108 (Box 1)
  - Acc. 1999-0470 (Box 1)
  - Acc. 2000-0221 (Box 1-2)
- Accession (2007-0111), 1 box
  Addition (07-111) (300 items, 0.4 lin. ft.; dated 2005) contains a constitution, executive committee files, meeting files, financial statements, publishing agreements, and other files related to the operation of the society in 2005. Also included are organizational files for the 2005 conference.
- Accession (2009-0124), 17 boxes
  Addition (09-124) (19,125 items; 25.5 lin. ft.; dated 1999-2008) consists of accepted and rejected manuscripts for the Journal of the History of Economic Thought.
  - March 1999 (Box 1)
  - June 1999 (Box 1)
  - September 1999 (Box 1)
  - December 1999 (Box 2)
  - March 2000 (Box 2)
  - June 2000 (Box 2)
  - September 2000 (Box 3)
  - December 2000 (Box 3)
  - March 2001 (Box 3)
  - June 2001 (Box 4)
  - September 2001 (Box 4)
  - December 2001 (Box 4)
  - March 2002 (Box 5)
  - June 2002 (Box 5)
  - September 2002 (Box 5)
  - December 2002 (Box 5)
  - December 2002 (Box 6)
  - March 2003 (Box 6)
  - June 2003 (Box 6)
  - September 2003 (Box 6)
  - September 2003 (Box 7)
  - December 2003 (Box 7)
  - March 2004 (Box 7)
  - March 2004 (Box 8)
  - June 2004 (Box 8)
  - September 2004 (Box 8)
  - December 2004 (Box 8)
  - December 2004 (Box 9)
  - March 2005 (Box 9)
  - June 2005 (Box 9)
  - September 2005 (Box 9)
  - September 2005 (Box 10)
  - December 2005 (Box 10)
  - March 2006 (Box 10)
  - June 2006 (Box 10)
  - September 2006 (Box 11)
  - December 2006 (Box 11)
  - March 2007 (Box 11)
  - June 2007 (Box 12)
  - September 2007 (Box 12)
  - December 2007 (Box 12)
  - March 2008 (Box 13)
  - June 2008 (Box 13)
  - September 2008 (Box 13)
  - December 2008 (Box 14)
  - Rejected manuscripts, 1999-2008, A-C (Box 14)
  - Rejected manuscripts, 1999-2008, C-H (Box 15)
  - Rejected manuscripts, 1999-2008, H-P (Box 16)
  - Rejected manuscripts, 1999-2008, P-S (Box 17)
- Accession (2015-0086), 1989-2008
  Scope and Contents
  Materials collected by Malcolm Rutherford during his presidency of the HES.
  - President's handbook (binder), undated (Box 15/083: 1)
    Includes administrative and logistical materials for the HES president, including budget, constitution, meeting minutes, etc.
  - HES President-Elect, 1995 (Box 15/083: 1)
  - Business, 1995-1997 (Box 15/083: 1)
  - JHET publisher, 1995-1997 (Box 15/083: 1)
  - UBC Conference preparations, 1995-1996; 8 folders (Box 15/083: 1-2)
    Includes conference planning materials, including correspondence witth guest speaker Axel Leijonhufvud and other program items.
  - Distinguished fellow, 1995-1998 (Box 15/083: 2)
  - Dorfman award, 1996 (Box 15/083: 2)
  - Nominations Committee, 1995-1997 (Box 15/083: 2)
  - Best Paper Committee, 1996-1997 (Box 15/083: 2)
  - HES Archives (at Duke), 1997 (Box 15/083: 2)
  - Charleston meeting, 1997 (Box 15/083: 2)
  - HES Vice President and AEA sessions, 1989-1992 (Box 15/083: 2)
  - JHET editorship, 1998 (Box 15/083: 2)
  - HES Perspectives volume, 1998 (Box 15/083: 2)
  - Nominations, 1999 (Box 15/083: 2)
  - Secretary/Treasurer, 1999 (Box 15/083: 2)
  - Joan Davis: UBC Conference; Dan Hammond: Wake Forest Conference, 1999-2000 (Box 15/083: 2)
  - O'Brien DF nomination, 2002 (Box 15/083: 2)
  - JHET editor search, 2007-2008 (Box 15/083: 2)
- Accession (2016-0285), 2015-2016, 0.1 Linear Feet
  Materials related to the ratification of a new HES constitution, meeting minutes, and committee correspondence.
  - Reform committee correspondence, Feb. 2015-April 2016 (Box 16/0285: 1)
  - Executive committee meeting minutes, January 2016 (Box 16/0285: 1)
  - Ratification of new constitution correspondence, April 2016 (Box 16/0285: 1)
  - Membership list, undated (Box 16/0285: 1)
- Accession (2017-0101), 2002-2005; 0.25 Linear Feet
  Contains printed email correspondence of Roy Weintraub related to his tenure as president of HES.
  - HES president e-correspondence, 2002-2005; 2 Files (Box 17/0101: 1)